Guide to the Herman Stearns Davis Papers, 1893-1932 AIS.1964.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Herman Stearns Davis Papers
1893-1932
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Davis, Herman Stearns
AIS.1964.23
5.18 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
Herman Stearns Davis, an astronomer educated at Princeton and Columbia University, worked for Columbia University, the U.S Coast and Geodetic Survey, the International Latitude Observatory, the cities of Pittsburgh and New York, the Gulf Refining Company and the Carnegie Institution during his career. The collection contains personal correspondence, a manuscript, notebooks, and newspaper clippings pertaining to astronomy.
Biography
Herman Stearns Davis, an astronomer, was born August 6, 1868, in Milford, DE. Davis graduated cum laude from Princeton University in 1892 and received his A.M degree (1894) and Ph.D.(1895) from Columbia University. From 1895-1899, Davis served as a professor of astronomy and geodessy at Columbia. In 1900 he became assistant at the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey and went on to serve as director of the International Latitude Observatory in Gaithersburg, MD until 1905. Davis then served as construction engineer and auditor for the cities of Pittsburgh and New York until 1910. From 1910 until 1920, he was the secretary to the President of Gulf Refining Co. in Pittsburgh and served as astronomer of the Carnegie Institution.
The majority of Davis' research was for the New Reduction of Piazzi's Star Catalog which he began in 1895. He also authored Glossary to Homer's Illiad in 1888, Parallax of Eta Cassiopeia in 1895, Catalogue of 62 Stars about Eta Cassiopeia in 1895, Computation Forms for the Use of Classes in Practical Astronomy in 1897, An Abbreviated Form of Least Square Solutions in 1898, Private Cipher-Book in 1911 and the Dictionary of Telegraphic Code-Words in 1912. Davis died in Pittsburgh on May 23, 1933.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains personal correspondence for the period 1894-1932. It also contains letterbooks from 1893-1904 and 1910, and a letterpressbook from 1895. Included are typed letters signed (T.L.S.) from Pierre du Pont, Sen. Mark Hannah, Sen. Henry Cabot Lodge, and Theodore Roosevelt. The collection contains a manuscript of Davis' article, "The Parallax of N. Cassiopeiae Deduced from the Rutherford Photographic Measures" (1895), five notebooks on "The New Reduction of Piazzi's Star Observations", a commonplace book, and newsclippings about astronomy from 1922-1930.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift of Nicholas E. Wagman in 1964.
Previous Citation
Herman Stearns Davis Papers,1893-1932, AIS.1964.23, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Davis, Herman Stearns, 1868-1933, Papers, 1893-1932, ais 64:23, Archives of Industrial Society
Personal papers; Astronomers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Davis, Herman Stearns; Du Pont, Pierre S. (Pierre Samuel); Gulf Refining Co; Hanna, Marcus Alonzo -- Correspondence; Lodge, Henry Cabot -- Correspondence; Princeton University; Roosevelt, Theodore -- Correspondence; Carnegie Institute; Columbia University
- Correspondence, 1894-1932; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains correspondence from 1894-1932 with some years missing. This series includes typed letters signed from Pierre du Pont (in folder 19), three members of the House of Representatives, nineteen United States Senators and two state governers. Folder 10 consists mainly of letters of recommendations sent to John Long, Secretary of the Navy for Davis to gain professorship at the U.S. Naval Observatory. Correspondence includes both autographed letters signed (A.L.S.) and typed letters signed (T.L.S.) from such notables as John Bassett Moore, Col. H.A. duPont, Gov. Foster Voorhees (NJ), Gov Elbe Tunnel (DE), Congressmen Charles Allen (MA), John Heffacker (DE), Lemuel Quigg (former Rep. from NY), John Dalzell (PA), and United States Senators George Wellington (MD), J.C. Burrows (MI), Stephen Elkins (WV), Joseph Hawley (CN), John Kean (NJ), William Allison (IW), Jacob Gallinger (NH), John Spooner (WI), William Frye (ME), Redfield Proctor (VT), Richard Kenney (DE), Cushman Davis (MN), George Gray (former Senator from DE), Thomas Platt (NY), A.O. Bacon (GA), William Mason (IL), Chauncey DePew (NY), Alexander Clay (GA), and William Sewell (former Senator from NJ).
  - 1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - January-June, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - July-December, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - January-June, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - July-December, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - January-June, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - July-December, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1900 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1901-1904 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - undated, ca.1899-1904 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1910 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1915 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1917 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1920 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1922 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1923 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1924 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1925 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1926 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1927 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1928 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 1929 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 1930 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1931 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1932 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Letterbooks, 1893-1904, 1910; II.
  Series II consists of 12 letterbooks which include T.L.S. from 1 member of the House of Representatives, 4 United States Senators, including Mark Hannah and Henry Cabot Lodge, and New York Governor Theodore Roosevelt. These letters are contained in Folder 35. Folder 31 consists of letters from Professor T.H. Saford, Ph.D principally in relation to "Declinations of 56-Stars." Folder 36 includes a letter from Rep. William Chanler.
  - 1893-1896 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - 1894-95 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - 1896-1897 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - 1897-1898 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - 1898-1899 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - 1899 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - 1899-1900 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - 1901 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - 1902-1903 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - 1903-1904 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - 1904 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - 1905 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Letterpress copybook, 1895; III.
  Series III contains Davis's letterpress copybook from 1895. Orginal correspondence and letter replys are included in the copybook.
  - 1895 (Box 6, Folder 42)
- Personal Material, IV.
  This series includes publications by Davis, information on several organizations such as the American Astronomical Society, the Education Alliance, the International Astronomical Union, the National Research Council, The People's University Extension Society of Greater New York, and the Second Conference of Astronomers and Astrophysicists. The series also contains information regarding 38 observatories worldwide that Davis was collecting for the Astronomical Directory (1898). Personal memorabilia is also included.
  - Publications by Davis (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Organizations (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Observatories (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Personal Memorabilia (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Observations, V.
  Series V contains a collection of observations including 11 of Davis' notebooks, five of which deal with The New Reduction of Piazzia's Star Observations, as well as one mechanical drawing and a photograph.
  - Notebooks, 1.
    - Astronomical tables and computer's handbook (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Double of Binary Stars (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Least squares solutions (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Logarithms (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Index to Star Catalog (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Transit factors for Palermo (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - New Reduction of Piazzi's Star Observations, 2.
    - Bibliography of Star Catalogs (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Form a-h (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Subject 5 + 6 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Right ascension and declination (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Index forms to n, p, table of instrument corrections, (First, approx.), tabulation of Piazzi's notes on quality of the night's observations as printed in Storia Celeste (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Unbound Notes and Drawings, 3.
    - Notes, unbound, undated (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Mechanical Drawings (Box 7, Folder 59)
- Commonplace Book, 1873-1896; VI.
  Series VI contains a scrapbook of non-astronomy related newsclippings.
  - 1873-1896 (Box 7, Folder 60)
- Astronomy, Newspaper Clippings, 1922-1930; VII.
  This series contains newspaper clippings about astronomy from 1922 to 1930.
  - 1922-1930 (Box 7, Folder 61)